Jay Street Firehouse Records, 1972-1981 RG.16
Poly Archives & Special Collections at Bern Dibner Library of Science and Technology
Guide to the Jay Street Firehouse Records, 1972-1981
RG.16
Poly Archives & Special Collections at Bern Dibner Library of Science and Technology
1.5 Cubic feet
In 1976, the Polytechnic Institute of Brooklyn entered into a long-term lease with the City of New York to acquire the Jay Street Brooklyn Firehouse (also known as the Old Brooklyn Firehouse). Paul DeCicco and other administrators at Poly worked with architect William A. Hall for over a decade to design, plan, and fundraise for the firehouse renovations.
Polytechnic Institute of Brooklyn.
Biographical/Historical note
The Old Brooklyn Firehouse was designed in 1892 by Frank Freedman. The red brick Romanesque-style building served as Brooklyn’s fire headquarters until 1972. Its seven story tower – then the tallest structure around – enabled fire watchers to detect blazes around the borough. If billows of smoke were spotted, horse-drawn fire wagons were dispatched from the firehouse located at 365-367 Jay Street between Myrtle Avenue and Willoughby Street. In 1972, it was included in the National Register of Historic Places.
Later that same year, the Polytechnic Institute of Brooklyn developed interest in purchasing and renovating the Jay Street Firehouse. After years of negotiation and planning, Poly entered long-term lease with the City of New York to develop a fire research center at the site in June 1976.
Paul DeCicco, director of Poly’s Center for Urban and Environmental Studies, spearheaded the development of the Fire Research Center. Working with Architect William A. Hall and administrators at Polytechnic, the building was designed to include a demonstration laboratory, a large computer display to simulate fires and firefighting situations, and a low speed wind tunnel to study fire phenomena. The center also included classrooms, training areas, a fire reference library, as well as assembly and gallery space for public exhibitions and performances. Proposals for the building included a shared space with the Poly Media Institute.
The project was funded by the Max C. Fleischmann Foundation; the New York State Department of Parks and Recreation, the U.S. Department of Housing and Urban Development, and the U.S. Department of the Interior Heritage Conservation and Recreation Service. The remainder came from private donations.
Scope and Contents note
The Jay Street Firehouse Records (1972-1981) chronologically document the acquisition and renovation plans of the Old Brooklyn Fire House. The collection includes correspondence, architectural plans, meeting minutes and notes, grant proposals, papers, reports, press releases, contract agreements, building leases, newspaper clippings, and a certificate of landmark appropriateness.
Conditions Governing Access note
Open for research without restrictions.
Arrangement note
The Jay Street Firehouse Records collection is arranged chronologically in one series. Box #2 contains oversized material such as architectual plans and community board form.
Related Material at the Poly Archives
Center for Urban Environmental Studies (CUES) Records
Bugliarello, George, (Georgio Bugliarello-Wondrich), 1927-2011; DeCicco, Paul; Downtown Brooklyn Development.; Max C. Fleischman Foundation .; New York (City). Dept. of City Planning. Housing & Community Development Section .; New York (City). Dept. of Real Estate.; New York City Fire Department .; William A. Hall & Associates.; Administrative records; Architecture (discipline); Articles; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Clippings; Correspondence; Grant proposals; Memoranda; Minutes; Pamphlets; Publications; Reprints
- Series I: Jay Street Firehouse Records, 1972-1981
  - Correspondence, 1972 November-December (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1973 March-December (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Poly Media Institute Proposal, circa 1973 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1974 January-May (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Building Utilization Study, 1974 May 13 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1974 September-December (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Historic Preservation Grants-In-Aid Instructions for Applications, 1975 March (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1975 January-February (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1975 January 28, April 3 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1975 April-July (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Statements Concerning the Jay Street Firehouse by George Bugliarello, 1975 August-December (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Background Information Request of Polytechnic Institute of New York for Use of Former Jay Street Fire Station in Brooklyn, 1975 October 2 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, 1975 October-November (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Board of Estimates Meeting Transcriptions, 1975 August-December (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, 1975 December (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, 1976 January-February (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Draft Proposal to the Fleischman Foundation, 1976 February (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Press Release: Polytechnic to Hose Public Service Program on Fire Safety, circa 1976 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence, 1976 March (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence, 1976 April (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence, 1976 May-June (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Building Lease, 1976 June (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Proposal Information for Fire Research Center, 1976 June 11 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Correspondence, 1976 June (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Correspondence, 1976 August-September (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Fire Officers News Bulletin-Brooklyn Fire Statistics, 1977 January (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Correspondence, 1977 January-March (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Correspondence, 1977 April-May (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Exterior Restoration Report, 1977 June 6 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Correspondence, 1977 June (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Building Lease, 1977 June (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Agreement with William A. Hall & Associates, 1977 June 8 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Building Lease, 1977 June (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Correspondence, 1977 July (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Annual Report to the Max C. Fleischman Foundation, 1977 July 29 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Correspondence, 1977 August-October (Box 1, Drawer 36)
  - Correspondence, 1977 November-December (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Feasibility Study, 1977 December 8 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Agreement with William A. Hall & Associates and Amendment, 1978 January and June (Box 1, Drawer 39)
  - Correspondence, 1978 January-February (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Correspondence, 1978 May-June, 1978 June (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Correspondence, 1978 July-August (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Center for Fire and Energy Research Report, 1978 July (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Correspondence, 1978 February-May (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Correspondence, 1978 August-October (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Urban Reinvestment Task Force Proposal Draft, 1978 October 24 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Correspondence, 1978 November-December (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Landmarks Preservation Commission Certificate of Appropriateness, No. 602, 1978 December 1 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Firehouse Material for Community Development Funds Proposal Draft, 1978 December 5 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Correspondence, 1978 February-March 9 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Correspondence, 1979 March 12-13 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Correspondence, 1979 March 14 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Correspondence, 1979 March 16-30 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Correspondence, 1979 August (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Correspondence, 1979 September (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Correspondence, 1979 January (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Correspondence, 1979 February-March (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Correspondence, 1979 April (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Audiovisual Facilities Study Report for Fire Research Center and Related Educational Faciltiy, 1979 April 17 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Draft Proposal Programs and Facilities for Fire Investigation, 1979 April 19 (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Correspondence, 1979 May-June (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Correspondence, 1979 July-August (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Manual for Public Participation in the Fiscal Year 1981 Budget Process, City of New York, 1979 August (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - Correspondence, 1979 October-December (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - Correspondence, 1980 January (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - Correspondence, 1980 February (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - Correspondence, 1980 March (Box 1, Folder 67)
  - Correspondence, 1980 April-May (Box 1, Folder 68)
  - Correspondence, 1980 June-July (Box 1, Folder 69)
  - Correspondence, 1980 August-September (Box 1, Folder 70)
  - Correspondence, 1980 October-December (Box 1, Folder 71)
  - Correspondence, 1981 October-December (Box 1, Folder 72)
  - William A. Hall & Associates Plans, 1979 October, undated (Box 2, Oversize 1)
  - Community Board Number 2, Borough of Brooklyn, Capital/Community Development Project Priorities and Requests Form, circa 1980 (Box 2, Oversize 2)